Guide to the Arnold Oscar Wolfers Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Arnold Oscar Wolfers papers
1903-1973
MS 634
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13.25
(31 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, and writings which document Wolfers's academic and administrative career in economics and international relations. Wolfers destroyed his files in 1949, upon retiring as Master of Pierson College, in 1957, when he became professor emeritus at Yale, and again in 1966 when he retired from the Center for Political Research. The files which remain, therefore, are not representative of the full scope of Wolfers's activities and collegial and personal relationships.
Wolfers, Arnold, 1892-1968
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were the gift of Mrs. Arnold O. (Doris) Wolfers, 1969.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence and Topical Files, 1903-1973. II. Writings, 1911-1969.
Scope and Contents
The Arnold O. Wolfers papers consist of correspondence, topical files, and writings which document Wolfers's academic and administrative career in economics and international relations. The papers were the gift of Mrs. Arnold O. (Doris) Wolfers in 1969. The 13.25 linear feet of material are arranged in two series.
SERIES I, CORRESPONDENCE AND TOPICAL FILES, consists of correspondence with friends and colleagues, materials relating to organizations with which Wolfers was involved, publications and invitations to speak and write reviews, and personal files. The correspondence files also include condolence letters written to Mrs. Wolfers after the death of her husband. Wolfers destroyed his files in 1949, upon retiring as Master of Pierson College, in 1957, when he became professor emeritus of Yale, and again in 1966 when he retired from the Center for Poltical Research. The files which remain, therefore, are not representative of the full scope of Wolfers's activities and collegial and personal relationships.
Correspondence with friends and colleagues Alice and Julius Schmidhauser, Ernst Krenek, Dietrich Schindler, and his father-in-law Robert Forrer contain discussions of books, articles, and politics. Topical files include a minimal amount of material documenting Wolfers's involvement with the Deutsche Hochschule für Politik, the World Peace Foundation's Franco-American Conference, the Interim Council on Security and Defense Affairs, the United States Army War College, and the Yale Institute of International Studies. Personal files consist of certificates and diplomas, date books, and photographs.
SERIES II, WRITINGS, contains a large number of unpublished addresses, articles, course lecture notes, lectures, and notes written by Wolfers over the course of his career. These include addresses and lectures delivered at Yale University and the National War College. Also included in this series are many of his published articles, chapters, and books dating from 1917 to 1968. Writings of Julius Schmidhauser and Carl Schmitt, and photocopies of memoirs of Mrs. Doris Wolfers are included at the end of the series.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Arnold O. Wolfers was born on June 14, 1892 in St. Gallen, Switzerland, the son of Otto Gustav and Clara Hirschfield Wolfers. He graduated summa cum laude from the University of Zurich in 1917 with a degree in law. In 1917 Wolfers was admitted to the Swiss bar and he practiced law in St. Gallen from 1917 to 1919. From 1919 to 1924, Wolfers studied economics and political science in Switzerland, Germany, Britain, and the United States. He received a Ph.D. from the University of Giessen in 1924. From 1924 to 1930 he was a lecturer in political science at the Hochschule für Politik in Berlin, where he organized a new department of international studies. He became director of the Hochschule in 1930. From 1930 to 1933 he was a privadozent in economics at the University of Berlin.
Wolfers came to the United States in 1933, and was appointed visiting professor in international relations at Yale University in the same year. In 1935 he became a professor of international relations, and in 1949 he was named Sterling Professor of International Relations at Yale as well as the first director of the Division of Social Sciences. He was Master of Pierson College from 1935 to 1949.
Wolfers retired from Yale in 1957, and became the founding director of the Washington Center of Foreign Policy Research, an affiliate of the School of Advanced International Studies of The Johns Hopkins University in Washington. He retired from the position in 1965, but remained affiliated with the Center as a special advisor and research associate.
In addition to his teaching and adminstrative career, Wolfers was president of the World Peace Foundation in 1953; was a member of the resident faculty of the National War College in 1947, and a member of its board of consultants from 1947 to 1951. He was a special advisor to and lecturer at the School of Military Government in Charlottesville, Virginia from 1942 to 1944. He was a consultant to the Office of Strategic Services from 1944 to 1945, to the Civilian Advisory Group of the Army War College in 1962, and to the Institute of Defense Analysis from 1960 until his death. He was a member of the Council of the Institute for Strategic Studies in London in 1964.
In addition to many articles and chapters, Wolfers wrote Britain and France Between Two Wars (1940) and Discord and Collaboration (1962). He co-edited with L. Martin The Anqlo-American Tradition (1956), and edited and co-authored Alliance Policy in the Cold War (1959). He founded the journal World Politics.
Wolfers died on July 16, 1968. That year, a professorship was established in his name at Yale University.
International relations; Philosophy; Political science -- Study and teaching; Educators; Schindler, Dietrich, 1864-; Schmidhauser, Julius, 1893-; Tillich, Paul, 1886-1965; Wolfers, Arnold, 1892-1968; Washington Center for Foreign Policy Research; Yale University -- Faculty
- CORRESPONDENCE AND TOPICAL FILES, 1903-1973; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The material within this series is arranged alphabetically by name of individual (for the correspondence files) and by type of material and/or organization or institution (for the topical files). Letters from unidentified correspondents and condolence letters received by Mrs. Wolfers after the death of her husband follow the alphabetical run of correspondence.
  - Correspondence
    - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ba-Be (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bi-Bla (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bo-Bru (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bu-Buz (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ca-Cl (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Co-Cu (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Da-Daw (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - De-Du (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - E (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - F (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Forrer, Robert, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - G (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ha-Hin (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ho-Hy (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - I (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - J (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Ka-Ke (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Kha-Ku (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Krenek, Ernst, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - L (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Ma-Man (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Mar-My (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Na-Nei (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - No-O (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - P-Q (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - R (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Sa-Sch (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Schindler, Dietrich, 1940-1966 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Schmidhauser, Alice, 1946-1960, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Schmidhauser, Julius (Gralai), 1923-1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Sco-Spy (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Sta-Step (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Ster-Sz (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - T-U (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Tillich, Paul J., 1923-1963 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - V (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Wa-Wh (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Wi-Wy (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - XYZ (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Unidentified (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Condolence letters: colleagues (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Condolence letters: former students (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Condolence letters: miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Condolence letters: official (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Condolence letters: personal (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Topical Files
    - Articles, book reviews, etc: requests declined, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Articles, book reviews, etc: requests declined, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Conference on Theory of International Politics, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Deutsche Hochschule für Politik, 1929/1930- 1933/1944 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Franco-American Conference: Duroselle, Jean B., 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Franco-American Conference: fund letters, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Franco-American Conference: fund letters, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Franco-American Conference: general correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Franco-American Conference: Goormaghtigh, John, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Franco-American Conference: paper delivered (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Franco-American Conference: printed material, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Franco-American Conference: program committee correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Interim Council on Security and Defense Affairs, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Lecture and conference invitations, declined, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Personal files
      - Awards
        General
        See: box 6, folder 90a See: box 6, folder 90b
      - Academic and government appointments, 1926-1965 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      - Arnold Wolfers Professorship, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - Biographical information, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - Biographical information: clippings, 1919-1965 (Box 4, Folder 65)
      - Certificates, 1892-1967 (Box 4, Folder 66)
        See also: Common Folio box 4, folder 72
      - Certificates (cont'd), 1892-1967 (Box 32)
      - Date books, 1956-1959 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - Date books, 1960-1967 (Box 5, Folder 68-69)
      - Diplomas: honorary, 1934-1965 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - Miscellaneous notes and receipts, 1923-1966 (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - Passports, 1939-1973 (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - Photographs: military, 1903, 1915, undated (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - Photographs: group, 1943-1965, undated (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - Photographs: portrait, 1952, undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - Photographs: portrait (cont'd), 1952, undated (Box 32)
      - Pierson College, Yale University: Wolfers portrait, 1951-1958 (Box 5, Folder 76)
      - St. Gallen High School diploma, 1905 (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - Speaking engagement lists, 1933-1956 (Box 5, Folder 78)
      - Swiss Army military service, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 79)
      - Swiss Army military service (cont'd), 1911 (Box 32)
      - University of Berlin, 1913-1923 (Box 5, Folder 80)
      - University of Berlin (cont'd), 1913-1923 (Box 5)
      - University of Lausanne, 1912-1913 (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - University of Munich, 1913-1923-1924 (Box 5, Folder 82)
      - University of Munich (cont'd), 1913-1923-1924 (Box 32)
      - University of Zurich, 1915-1917 (Box 6, Folder 83)
      - University of Zurich (cont'd), 1915-1917 (Box 32)
    - Red Cross International Committee, 1961-1962, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 84-85)
    - United nations Association, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - United Nations Army War, College, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - World Peace Foundation, undated (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Yale Institute of International Studies: correspondence, 1948-1951 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Yale Institute of International Studies: newspaper clippings, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Awards
      - Das Grosse Verdieust Kreuz, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 90a)
      - National War College, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 90b)
- WRITINGS, 1911-1969; Series II
  The material within this series is arranged alphabetically by type of writing. Published articles, chapters, and books are interfiled within "publications." Material within each writing type is arranged chronologically. Writings of others and Wolfers's research note cards follow the writings of Wolfers.
  - Addresses, 1933-1939 (Box 7, Folder 91-103)
  - Addresses, 1940-1944 (Box 8, Folder 104-113)
  - Addresses, 1945-1947 (Box 9, Folder 114-123)
  - Addresses, 1948-1952 (Box 10, Folder 124-133)
  - Addresses, 1953-1959 (Box 11, Folder 134-143)
  - Addresses, 1960-1966, undated (Box 12, Folder 144-151)
  - Articles, 1911-1925 (Box 12, Folder 152-154)
  - Articles, 1927-1966 undated (Box 13, Folder 155-170)
  - Bibliographies, undated (Box 14, Folder 171-173)
  - Book manuscript, untitled, undated (Box 14, Folder 174-179)
  - Book outlines, Circa1920, 1922-1926 (Box 14, Folder 180-182)
  - Book outlines, 1940-1967 (Box 15, Folder 183-192)
  - Book outlines, undated (Box 16, Folder 193-194)
  - Book reviews, 1936, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 195)
  - Course lecture notes, 1930-ca. 1950s (Box 16, Folder 196-206)
  - Course syllabus: Foundations of National Power, 1944-1945 (Box 17, Folder 207)
  - Dissertation written for law degree, 1924 (Box 17, Folder 208)
  - Fellowship drafts, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 209)
  - Lectures, 1924-1962 (Box 17, Folder 210-219)
  - Lectures, 1965-1967 (Box 18, Folder 220-222)
  - Lectures: Current event talks at Pierson College, Yale University, 1934-1946 (Box 18, Folder 223-228)
  - Lectures: National War college, 1946-1951 (Box 18, Folder 229-231)
  - Lectures: National War college, 1961 (Box 19, Folder 232-233)
  - Memoranda, 1932-1962 (Box 19, Folder 234-238)
  - Miscellaneous, 1916-1931, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 239)
  - Notes, 1923-1963 (Box 19, Folder 240-244)
  - Notes: Julius Ceasar, 1903 (Box 19, Folder 245)
  - Notes: topics, undated (Box 19, Folder 246)
  - Outlines, 1950 (Box 19, Folder 247)
  - Outlines, 1958-1965 (Box 20, Folder 248-253)
  - Publications
    - 1917, 1923, 1925 (Box 20, Folder 254-256)
    - 1926-1928, 1930 (Box 20, Folder 257-263)
    - 1931-1940 (Box 21, Folder 264-271)
    - 1940-1946 (Box 21, Folder 272-277)
    - 1947, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 278-282)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 22, Folder 283-286)
    - 1952-1956 (Box 23, Folder 287-292)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 24, Folder 293-298)
    - 1959 (Box 25, Folder 299-308)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 26, Folder 309-321)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 27, Folder 322-332)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 28, Folder 333-338)
    - 1966, 1968, undated (Box 29, Folder 339-343)
  - Writings of others
    - Schmidhauser, Julius, 1922, 1927, undated (Box 29, Folder 344-345)
    - Schmidhauser, Julius, 1961, undated (Box 30, Folder 346-350)
    - Schmitt, Carl. Excerpts from "Der Begriff des politischen,", 1964 (Box 30, Folder 351)
    - Wolfers, Doris (Mrs. Arnold), 1969 (Box 30, Folder 352)
  - Research note cards, undated (Box 31)